we're kicking off a three video series
on
hair loss
what causes it and what can drug
supplements and foods do to help prevent
or reverse it
watch the videos to find out i know i'm
going to
[Music]
studies show that by age 50
approximately half
of men and women will experience hair
loss
no it's not caused by washing your hair
too much or brushing your hair too
little two of the many myths out there
the majority of hair loss with age is
genetic for both women and men in the
case of this study based on twin studies
the heritability of baldness in men's 79
percent meaning about 80 percent of the
difference in hair loss between men
is genetically determined but that still
leaves some wiggle room
even if you have identical twins
identical twin sisters in this case with
the same dna one can have more hair loss
than the other thanks to increased
stress increased smoking having more
children or having a history of high
blood pressure or cancer
for example check out these two
identical twin brothers same genes but
the twin on the right reported more
stress in their life
in this pair the identical twin on the
right was a smoker and drank more
alcohol
smoking can contribute to the
development of both male and female
pattern baldness because of the
genotoxic compounds in cigarettes may
damage the dna and hair follicles and
cause
microvascular poisoning in the base of
the follicle
other toxic agents associated with hair
loss include mercury
because it seems to concentrate about
250 fold in growing scalp hair
in fact maybe the reason shakespeare
started losing his hair was due to
mercury poisoning from syphilis
treatment
thankfully doctors don't give people
mercury anymore
these days as the cdc points out mercury
mainly enters the body through seafood
consumption
women of reproductive age frequently
seek treatment for what is thought to be
hormone-related hair loss especially at
menopause but for example this woman
came in with hair loss and blood tests
indicated elevated mercury levels and no
wonder as she had a diet high in tuna
but the good news is that her mercury
levels fell with elimination of dietary
tuna
within two months her hair started to
come back in seven months maintaining a
fish free diet her hair completely
regrow
so doctors should consider screening for
mercury toxicity when they see hair loss
since there's something we can do about
it
instructing patients to reduce fish
intake and repeat blood tests could
offer relief of symptoms and uncover
dietary habits that may be a source of
heavy metal induced hair loss
though admittedly sometimes heavy metal
can lead to too much hair
what about nutrient deficiencies as a
cause of hair loss after bariatric
surgery the most frequent nutrient
deficiency symptom is hair loss but
that's because they've had their anatomy
rearranged to cause malabsorption on
purpose
in general there is little evidence to
suggest that vitamin and mineral
supplementation benefits people unless
they're actually deficient for example
we've known for centuries that scurvy
severe vitamin c deficiency can cause
hair loss
but once you have enough vitamin c such
that your gums aren't bleeding there's
no data correlating vitamin c levels and
hair loss once you have a certain
baseline sufficiency of vitamin c
it's also a myth that supplements
containing zinc will increase hair
growth unless you have zinc deficiency
like if you're an alcoholic or something
but if you have normal zinc levels in
your blood taking more zinc won't help
and in fact can have negative side
effects same thing with taking iron
supplements
the most common ingredient in top
selling hair loss products is vitamin b7
also known as biotin yes biotin
deficiency causes hair loss
but there are no evidence-based data
that supplementing biotin promotes hair
growth and severe biotin deficiency in
healthy individuals eating a normal diet
has never been reported but if you eat
raw egg whites you can acquire a biotin
deficiency since there are these
compounds that attach to biotin and
prevent it from being absorbed
but other than rare deficiency syndromes
it's a myth that biotin supplements
increase hair growth
but hey why not just have the attitude
can't hurt might help
because of the lack of regulatory
oversight of the supplement industry and
in the case of biotin interference with
lab tests
many dietary supplements promoted for
hair health contained biotin levels up
to 650 times the recommended daily
intake of biotin and excess biotin in
the blood can play haywire on a bunch of
different blood tests including thyroid
function and other hormone tests
including pregnancy
also the tests they do to see if you've
had a heart attack so it could
potentially even be life or death
and in terms of poor regulation as i've
done tons of videos about there are all
sorts of supplement manufacturer
shenanigans for example this outbreak in
which hundreds suffered selenium
toxicity
because they had an oopsie and put 200
times the dose and so it ended up
causing hair loss and the same thing can
happen with getting too much vitamin a
[Music]
you